<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="logic2" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Logical Arguments</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>




	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>



		<exercise>
			<title>Implications</title>
			<idx><h>Implications</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Write down the contrapositive, converse and inverse of the implication: "if <m>x &lt; 3</m> then <m>x^2 &lt; 9</m>." Which of these four statements are <em> true</em>? Which ones are <em> false</em>?


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Quantifiers</title>
			<idx><h>Quantifiers</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Let <m>X</m> be the set of people. Let <m>P(x,y)</m> be the statement "<m>x</m> loves <m>y</m>." Rewrite each of the following statements using formal quantifiers and variables.

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Everybody loves somebody.

					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
  Somebody loves everybody.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Negating Quantifiers</title>
			<idx><h>Negating Quantifiers</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Negate the formal statements you made in the previous problem, then translate them into everyday English. Do these negations make sense, when compared to the original statements?


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Fooling Around</title>
			<idx><h>Fooling Around</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Negate the statement "You can fool all of the people all of the time" by first creating a formal statement using quantifiers. Hint: you are considering two sets: <em>people</em> and <em>times</em>.


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Equivalent Statements</title>
			<idx><h>Equivalent Statements</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Use a truth table to show that <m>\neg (P \Rightarrow Q)</m> is equivalent to <m>P \wedge \neg Q</m>.

<me>
\begin{array}{c|c||c|c|c|c}
P &amp; Q &amp; P \Rightarrow Q &amp; \neg(P \Rightarrow Q)  &amp; \neg Q &amp; P \wedge \neg Q \\
\hline
T &amp; T &amp;  &amp;  &amp; &amp; \\
T &amp; F &amp;  &amp; &amp; &amp; \\
F &amp; T &amp;  &amp; &amp; &amp;\\
F &amp; F &amp;  &amp; &amp;  &amp;\\
\end{array}
</me>


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Negate the statement "For all <m>x \in \R</m>, if <m>x</m> is an integer then <m>x</m> is positive." Use part (a) to find an equivalent statement, and then explain why providing one counterexample is enough to disprove that <m>P \Rightarrow Q</m>


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>



				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Evaluating an Argument</title>
			<idx><h>Evaluating an Argument</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Determine the validity of the following arguments. Include a truth table to justify your conclusion.

			<ol>

				<li>
					<p>
 If I stay up late at night, then I will be tired in the morning. I am tired this morning. Therefore, I stayed up late last night.



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 If I stay up late at night, then I will be tired in the morning. I am not tired this morning. Therefore, I did not stay up late last night.





					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>






				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Evaluating Another Argument</title>
			<idx><h>Evaluating Another Argument</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Determine the validity of the following argument. Include a truth table to justify your conclusion.

			</p><p>

If I work hard, then I earn lots of money. If I earn lots of money, then I pay high taxes. Therefore, if I pay high taxes, then I have worked hard.



				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>

</chapter>
