<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="count-perm-comb" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Permutations and Combinations</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>


Here are the formulas to count  sublists and subsets of the set <m>[n] = \{1,2,\ldots, n\}</m>.
		<ul>
			<li>
			<p>
 A <em>permutation</em> of <m>[n]</m> is an ordered list of its elements. The number of permutations of <m>[n]</m> is
<me>
n! = n (n-1) (n-2) \cdots 2 \cdot 1.
</me>
			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 A  <m>k</m>-<em>list</em> of <m>[n]</m> (also called a <m>k</m><em>-permutation</em>) is an ordered list of <m>k</m> elements of <m>[n]</m>. The number of <m>k</m>-lists of <m>[n]</m> is
<me>
P(n,k) = (n)_k = n (n-1) \cdots (n-k+1).
</me>
			</p>
			</li>
			<li>
			<p>
 A <m>k</m><em>-set</em> of <m>[n]</m> (also called a <m>k</m><em>- combination</em>) is a subset containing <m>k</m> elements of <m>[n]</m>. The number of <m>k</m>-sets of <m>[n]</m> is
<me>
C(n,k) = {n \choose k} = \frac{n!}{k! (n-k)!}.
</me>
			</p>
			</li>
		</ul>




	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>

		<exercise>
			<title>Bus Stop</title>
			<idx><h>Bus Stop</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Four adults and seven children are waiting at a bus stop.

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many ways can they sit in a row?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many ways can they sit in a row if the adults must sit together and the childreh must sit together?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many ways can they sit in a row if the the children must sit together?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many ways can they sit in a row if <em>just</em> the children are sitting together (and the adults must not sit together)?


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>In the Queue</title>
			<idx><h>In the Queue</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
How many ways can 10 adults and 5 children stand in a line so that no two children are standing next to each other? (Hint: place the adults first, and then the children.)


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Forming a Circle</title>
			<idx><h>Forming a Circle</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
In how many ways can <m>n</m> people stand in a circle? (How is this problem different from standing in a line?)


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Five Digits, No Zeros</title>
			<idx><h>Five Digits, No Zeros</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many 5-digit numbers are there where no digit repeats and only the digits 1-9 appear?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Use inclusion-exclusion to determine how many numbers in part (a) contain a 3 and a 6. (Hint: you will need to use "good = all - bad.")


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Coin Toss</title>
			<idx><h>Coin Toss</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
A coin is tossed 10 times and a sequence of heads and tails is observed.

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many different sequences are possible?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 In how how many of these sequences are there exactly 4 heads?


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Dinner Party</title>
			<idx><h>Dinner Party</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
A woman has 9 close friends.

			<ol>

				<li>
					<p>
 In how many ways can she invite 6 of them to dinner?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Repeat (a) if two of her friends don't get along and will not attend together.


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Repeat (a) if her friends consist of 3 single people and 3 married couples, so that she must invite both spouses, or neither of them.


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>10 Points</title>
			<idx><h>10 Points</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Ten points in a plane, no three colinear, are given.

			<ol>


				<li>
					<p>
 Every pair of points determines a unique line. So how many different lines are formed by joining pairs of these points?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Assume that none of the lines in  part (a)  are parallel and no three lines intersect at a single point.  How many different triangles are formed by these lines? (Note that the corners of  many of these triangles
are at points other than the original 10 points!)


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Executive Board</title>
			<idx><h>Executive Board</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
How many ways can a club with 20 members choose an executive board consisting of a president, a secretary, a treasurer, and two other members?


				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>




</chapter>
