<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<chapter xml:id="count-include-exclude" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Inclusion/Exclusion</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>

	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>

		<exercise>
			<title>Rolling 10 Dice</title>
			<idx><h>Rolling 10 Dice</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
We roll 6-sided die 10 times, and then list the outcomes in order as <m>(x_1, x_2, \ldots , x_{10} )</m>. We are interested in counting the total number outcomes in which 1 or 2 appears at least once.  We break this process into multiple steps.

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Let <m>X</m> be the set of all possible outcomes <m>(x_1, x_2, \ldots , x_{10} )</m>. What is <m>|X|</m>?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Let <m>X_1</m> be the set of outcomes that <em>do not </em> contain any 1's. I would call <m>X_1</m> the set of "bad outcomes for 1." What is <m>|X_1|</m>?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Define <m>X_2</m> in the same way as in part (b), where <m>X_2</m> is the set of "bad outcomes for 2." What is <m>|X_2|</m>?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many outcomes are there in which neither 1 or 2 appears? How would you describe this set using the symbols <m>X_1</m> and <m>X_2</m>?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Use inclusion-exclusion to find the number of outcomes in which either 1 does not or appear or 2 does not appear (or both do not appear). This account for all the "bad outcomes."


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Now use your answer from part (d) to find the number of "good  outcomes." Namely, how many outcomes contain either 1 or 2 or both?


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>



				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>I Hate 2, 5, and 7</title>
			<idx><h>I Hate 2, 5, and 7</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
In this question, you will determine how many numbers between 1 and 140 are <em>not</em> divisible by any of 2, 5 or 7. As in the previous question, we  start by counting the complement of the set we are interested in (because it is easier to count).

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 Negate the statement "<m>n</m> is not divisible by any of 2, 5 and 7."


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 The set of numbers that you described in part (a) can be found using inclusion-exclusion. Do so.





					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Use your answer to (b) to find how many numbers in [140] are <em>not</em> divisible by any of 2, 5 and 7.


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>




</chapter>
