<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>


<chapter xml:id="count-warmup" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Basic Counting Problems</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>



	</p>
	</introduction>
	<exercises>
		<title>Practice Problems</title>



		<exercise>
			<title>Packing a Lunch</title>
			<idx><h>Packing a Lunch</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
A healthy lunch box contains a sandwich, a piece of fruit and a drink.
There are  six different types of sandwiches,   five kinds of fruit, and three drink flavors. How many different possible lunch boxes are there?



				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Buying Ice Cream</title>
			<idx><h>Buying Ice Cream</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
An ice cream store has five flavors of ice cream: vanilla, chocolate, strawberry, peppermint and bubble gum. When you order a cone, your options are sugar cone, waffle cone and cake cone.

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
  What is the total number of ways to order a single-scoop ice cream cone?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 Suppose that we want to order a triple-scoop cone at this ice cream store. Stacking scoops of ice cream is important: a peppermint-vanilla-vanilla cone tastes different from a vanilla-peppermint-vanilla cone. What is the total number of ways to order a triple-scoop ice cream cone?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 The ice cream store also sells quarts of ice cream. When you buy quarts of ice cream, the order that you buy the quarts does not matter: they just go into your shopping bag anyway!
How many ways can you buy two quarts of ice cream when ...

			<ol>

				<li>
					<p>
 Both quarts are the same flavor?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 The quarts are different flavors? (Remember that the order of the flavors doesn't matter!)


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>





					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>




				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<title>Ultimate Frisbee Tournament</title>
			<idx><h>Ultimate Frisbee Tournament</h></idx>
			<statement>
				<p>
Four teams are attends Ultimate frisbee tournament.


			<ol>

				<li>
					<p>
 If each team plays each other team exactly once, how many games are played?



					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 These four Ultimate teams decide to play a game for fun by mixing up the teams. They put red, blue, yellow and green armbands into a bag, and each player closes her eyes and grabs an armband to determine her team.

			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many armbands must be grabbed to ensure that one of the teams has two players?


					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
 How many armbands must be grabbed to ensure that one of the teams has five players?


					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>

					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>






				</p>
			</statement>
		</exercise>
	</exercises>


</chapter>
